Guide to the J. Walter Thompson Company. Detroit Office. Blaise Newman papers, 1946-2002 and undated RL.11676
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
J. Walter Thompson Company. Detroit Office. Blaise Newman papers
1946-2002 and undated
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
J. Walter Thompson Company. Detroit Office
John W. Hartman Center for Sales, Advertising & Marketing History
RL.11676
14.0 linear feet Linear Feet
Founded in 1864, the J. Walter Thompson Company (JWT) is one of the oldest and largest enduring advertising agencies in the United States. It is headquartered in New York. JWT maintained an office in Detroit from 1909-1920 and reopened it in 1944. Blaise Newman was an executive with the JWT Detroit Office, Director of Corporate Communications and Special Projects. Collection includes account files, correspondence, memorabilia, newsletters, print advertisements, research reports, scripts and drafts of speeches and presentations, slides and photographs, videocassettes, and other printed materials. Companies represented include Champion Spark Plug, Ford, Health Alliance Plan, Holley, Red Cross and United Way. Acquired as part of the John W. Hartman Center for Sales, Advertising & Marketing History.
Arrangement
Organized into the following series: Client Files; Correspondence; Events; General Office Files; Printed Material; Public Relations; Memorabilia; and Audiovisual Materials.
Biographical / Historical
Founded in 1864, the J. Walter Thompson Company (JWT) is one of the oldest and largest enduring advertising agencies in the United States. It is headquartered in New York. JWT maintained an office in Detroit from 1909-1920 and reopened it in 1944. Blaise Newman was an executive with the JWT Detroit Office, Director of Corporate Communications and Special Projects. Born 1932, Iowa. U.S. Army 1952-1954; graduated Wayne State University 1955; Engineering Sales Representative, Ford Motor Company 1955-1958; Account Representative, JWT Detroit 1958-1964; Manager, JWT New Orleans 1964; Instructor, Loyola University Department of Communications 1967-1968; Manager and Account Supervisor, JWT Kansas City 1972-1973; JWT Chicago 1973-1974; JWT Detroit 1974-2001; faculty, Davenport University, Detroit College of Business; died 2002, Michigan.
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
However, original audiovisual materials are closed until use copies can be produced.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. There may be a 48-hour delay in obtaining these materials.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The J. Walter Thompson Company. Detroit Office. Blaise Newman papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift in 1993-2002.
Related Materials
Related materials may be found in the following Hartman Center collections:
J. Walter Thompson Company. Account Files
J. Walter Thompson Company. Corporate Anniversaries
J. Walter Thompson Company. Domestic Advertisements
J. Walter Thompson Company. Writings and Speeches
Collection Overview
Collection includes account files, correspondence, memorabilia, newsletters, print advertisements, research reports, scripts and drafts of speeches and presentations, slides and photographs, videocassettes, and other printed materials. Companies represented include Champion Spark Plug, Ford, Health Alliance Plan, Holley, Red Cross and United Way. Acquired as part of the John W. Hartman Center for Sales, Advertising & Marketing History.
Advertising; Advertising -- United States -- History; Advertising agencies; Advertising agencies -- United States; Advertising agencies -- United States -- History; Advertising agencies -- Management; Advertising executives -- United States; John W. Hartman Center for Sales, Advertising & Marketing History; Burger King Corporation; Champion Spark Plug (Company); Ford Motor Company; American Red Cross
- Client Files, 1970-2001 and undated; 1
  - AAA Michigan, 1985 (Box 1)
  - Ames Department Stores, 1990 (Box 1)
  - ANCO, 1981-1982 and undated; 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Burger King--Photograph of presentation participants, undated (Box 1)
  - Carhartt, 1983 (Box 1)
  - Champion Spark Plug, 1981- 1984 and undated; 5 folders (Box 1)
  - Champion Spark Plug--Couponing exploration, 1981- 1984 and undated; 5 folders (Box 1)
  - Chatham Store, 1979 (Box 1)
  - Colorado Lottery (JWT Denver), 1982 (Box 1)
  - Detroit Police Officers Association Safety Vest Fund, 1987 (Box 1)
  - First Michigan Bank, 1986 (Box 1)
  - Ford, 1970-1995; 11 folders (Box 1)
  - Ford Detroit International Jazz Festival, 2000-2001 (Box 11)
  - Health Alliance Plan, 1985-1991; 3 folders (Box 1)
  - Holley, 1983-1984; 3 folders (Box 1)
  - International Federation of Multiple Schlerosis pamphlet, 1998 (Box 1)
  - Kellogg, 1989 (Box 1)
  - Kohl's, 1996 (Box 1)
  - Michigan Consolidated Gas, 1976-1987 (Box 2)
  - Monroe, 1986 (Box 2)
  - New York State Lottery, 1987 (Box 2)
  - North American Clients, 2000 (Box 2)
  - Red Cross, 1988-1995; 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Shopko, 1985 (Box 2)
  - Six Flags, 1983 (Box 2)
  - United Way, 1986-1987, 1997; 4 folders (Box 2)
  - U.S. Clients, 1999 (Box 2)
- Correspondence, 1973-1999; 2
  - Hartman Center, 1997 (Box 2)
  - Internal memos, 1981-1996; 15 folders (Box 2)
  - JWT external memos, 1989-1992; 4 folders (Box 2)
  - JWT external memos, 1993 (Box 3)
  - Reader files, 1973-1984; 24 folders (Box 3)
  - Reader files, 1984-1987; 19 folders (Box 4)
  - Reader files, 1987-1995; 21 folders (Box 5)
  - Reader files, 1995-1999; 15 folders (Box 6)
- Events, 1965-2001 and undated; 3
  - Advertising student campaign contest (University of Detroit), 1988 (Box 6)
  - Automotive Aftermarket Seminar, 1983 (Box 6)
  - Awards, 1990, 1998 (Box 6)
    Scope and Contents
    Includes nomination forms for 1990 Adcraft PM Award of Excellence (Joya Harris); 1998 Effie Awards (Ford Expedition, Monroe)
  - Central America press reception, 1996 (Box 6)
  - Certificate of Appreciation from Detroit Mayor Dennis Archer to Blaise Newman/JWT, 1996 (Box 11)
  - Conferences, 1989 (Box 6)
  - Detroit 300 (tricentennial), 2001 (Box 6)
  - Detroit Historical Museum Motor City Exhibition, 1996 (Box 6)
  - Detroit International Croquet Tournament (benefit for Boy Scouts), 1994 (Box 6)
  - Detroit Office Christmas party, 1992 (Box 6)
  - Drug Enforcement Agency benefit, 2001; 3 folders (Box 6)
  - Drug Enforcement Agency benefit (disk with Survivors Logo), 2001 (Box AV1)
  - FDAF (Ford Dealer Advertising Fund) Critics Award to Blaise Newman, 1965 (Box 6)
  - JWT 125th anniversary, 1989; 2 folders (Box 7)
  - JWT client Christmas party, 1989 (Box 7)
  - JWT Detroit Employees Anniversary Recognition Awards, 1988, 1990; 2 folders (Box 7)
  - Montreux Detroit Jazz Festival, 1997 (Box 7)
  - Phantom of the Opera, 1992 (Box 7)
  - Presentations, 1976-1991 (Box 7)
  - Seville European Managers Meeting, 1995 (Box 7)
  - Slides from presentation on Ford in Europe, undated (Box 7)
  - Speeches by Peter Schweitzer, 1986-1991; 2 folders (Box 7)
  - Ted Gushee retirement, 1993 (Box 7)
  - Thompson Nights, 1987 (Box 7)
  - WPP Atticus Awards, 1996 (Box 7)
- General Office Files, 1946-2002 and undated; 4
  - Administrative documents, 1989 and undated (Box 7)
  - Blaise Newman biographical, obituaries, 1958-2002; 2 folders (Box 7)
  - Budget, 1983 (Box 7)
  - Check Requests, 1999-2001; 4 folders (Box 7)
  - Clipping file--Interactive, 1995 (Box 7)
  - Clipping file--International advertising, 1988-1990 (Box 7)
  - Comparision Revenue/Direct Margins, 1982-1983 (Box 7)
  - Credentials, 1993 (Box 7)
  - Detroit office building, 1973-1974 (Box 7)
  - Employee benefits, 1990 (Box 7)
  - "Fieldmen" (account representatives), 1975; 2 folders (Box 7)
  - J. Walter Online, 1991 (Box 8)
  - JWT Chicago 1994 Strategic Plan, 1993 (Box 8)
  - JWT company history, 1946-1995; 2 folders (Box 8)
  - JWT company history--Detroit Office, 1987 (Box 8)
  - JWT company history--A Short History of the J. Walter Thompson Company Detroit Office, 2001 (Box 8)
  - JWT Detroit phone directory, 1995 (Box 8)
  - JWT direct mail program, 1985 (Box 8)
  - JWT employee survey, 1994; 2 folders (Box 8)
  - Move to 1 Detroit Center Building, 1983 (Box 8)
  - New Business Marketing/Communication Action Plan, 1976 (Box 8)
  - Professional Development, 1971-1990 and undated; 4 folders (Box 8)
  - Retail case histories, undated (Box 8)
  - Roderick v. Ford Motor Company deposition documents, 1989 (Box 8)
  - Speech (Blaise Newman)--Michigan Organization of Private Schools, 1987 (Box 8)
  - Strategic planning, 1978-1990 and undated (Box 8)
  - Sue Savage--Guiding Organizational Change, 1984 (Box 8)
  - Thank Yous, 1968-2001; 3 folders (Box 8)
  - The Golden Age of Radio, undated (Box 8)
  - Writings and speeches by JWT staff, 1960-1990 (Box 8)
  - Worldwide Home Address List, 1999 (Box 8)
  - Worldwide Office Address List, 1999 (Box 8)
  - Yearbook, 1996 (Box 8)
- Printed Materials, 1949-2002 and undated; 5
  - General, 1
    - 128 Years of Advertising Leadership, 1992 (Box 8)
    - Ad Day, 1988 (Box 8)
    - Adcrafter, 2001 (Box 8)
    - Advertising Age--JWT Centennial issue, 1964 (Box 11)
    - Advertising Production Club of Detroit--Galley Proof newsletter, 1983, 1990 (Box 8)
    - American Red Cross--Rhapsody in Red book, 1994 (Box 8)
    - Arthur White (Yankelovich)--The Charitable Behavior of Americans, undated (Box 8)
    - Champion Spark Plug--Making Champions, 1949 (Box 8)
    - Communications Forum paper 6--Public Relations: What It Isn't and Is (Wallace Clayton), undated (Box 8)
    - Crain's Detroit Business--Book of Lists, 2002 (Box 11)
    - Crain's Detroit Business--Detroit at 300, 2001 (Box 11)
    - Detroit College of Business Alumni Association quarterly report, 1989 (Box 8)
    - Detroit Country Day School newsletter, 1989 (Box 8)
    - Detroit Empowerment Zone pamphlets, approximately 1994 (Box 8)
    - Detroit News--Article on tree planting, 1995 (Box 8)
    - Detroit Police Officers Association--Tuebor newsletter with safety vest drive feature, 1987 (Box 11)
    - Detroit Thompson Times, 1979-1986 (Box 8)
    - Donovan Data Systems--DDS News, 1989 (Box 11)
    - Flippers: Changes in the Way Americans Watch TV, approximately 1986 (Box 8)
    - FOB Detroit, 1967-1973 (Box 8)
    - Ford World, 1988 (Box 11)
    - Greater Detroit Chamber of Commerce--Guide to Metro Detroit, 1982 (Box 8)
    - Henry Ford: We Had to Race commemorative edition 1897-1997 (Box 8)
    - J. Walter Merchandise catalogs, 1994-1997 (Box 8)
    - James B. Carl--Fish (for Epilepsy Foundation of Michigan), 1998 (Box 8)
    - JWT 125th Anniversary book, 1989 (Box 9)
    - JWT Advertising Leadership 1864-1989 (Box 11)
    - JWT Christmas songbook, undated (Box 9)
    - JWT Media Negotiating: The Rites of March, 1989 (Box 9)
    - JWTimes, 1997-1998 (Box 9)
    - Michigan Opera Theatre special 1998 commemorative issue (Box 11)
    - News from JWT Detroit, 1988-1993; 2 folders (Box 9)
    - Recruitment book, 1992; 3 folders (Box 9)
    - The Big Idea/Diary of a Concept--Iceland: It's Not Just for Bjork Anymore (Laura Monahan), 1998 (Box 11)
    - This Week in Detroit, 1956-1962; 3 folders (Box 9)
    - United Foundation--Torchlighter newsletter, 1987 (Box 11)
    - White Paper v1 no. 2: Does Advertising Work? A Review of the Evidence, 1990 (Box 9)
    - Young & Rubicam Detroit--Window Ledge newsletter, 1990 (Box 9)
  - JWT Media Resources and Research Department Reports, 1988-1989 and undated; 2
    - 1989-90 Program Schedule (Box 9)
    - Barter Syndication, 1989 (Box 9)
    - In Defense of Mass Media, 1989 (Box 9)
    - Magazine Inserts, 1989 (Box 9)
    - Media Systems Catalogue, 1989 (Box 9)
    - Out of Home TV Viewing, 1989 (Box 9)
    - Predicting the "Useful" Future, 1989 (Box 9)
    - Quarterly television analyses, 1989 (Box 9)
    - The Impact of Network Revenues on TV Advertising, undated (Box 9)
    - The World of Local Cable, 1989 (Box 9)
    - Top Executive Study, 1988 (Box 9)
    - Update on the Fox Network, 1989 (Box 9)
    - Update on the Viewership of Cable Networks, 1989 (Box 9)
    - VCRs Then and Now, 1989 (Box 9)
    - Year One of the People Meter, 1988 (Box 9)
- Public Relations, 1980-1999 and undated; 6
  - Clippings, 1980-1999; 5 folders (Box 9)
  - How to Deal with Broadcast and Print Interviews, 1990 (Box 9)
  - JWT News Releases, 1993-1996; 4 folders (Box 9)
  - PR Council, 1995-1998; 2 folders (Box 10)
  - Press releases, 1991-1999; 5 folders (Box 10)
  - Van Patrick Memorial Invitational golf tournament, 1989 (Box 10)
    Includes press release, photograph and biography of Miss America Gretchen Carlson
- Memorabilia, 1989-2002 and undated; 7
  - Desk thermometer, undated (Box 12)
  - Diamond Crystal cuff link and tie pin set in box, undated (Box 12)
  - Ford Global Business Unit coffee mug, undated (Box 12)
  - Ford/JWT 50th anniversary paperweight, 1994 (Box 12)
  - JWT 125th anniversary license plate, 1989 (Box 12)
  - JWT baseball cap, undated (Box 12)
  - JWT belt buckle, undated (Box 12)
  - JWT dashlight, undated (Box 12)
  - JWT key fobs, undated (Box 12)
  - JWT owl bookmark and 125th anniversary tie pin (6 pieces), 1989 (Box 12)
  - JWT mission statement medal, 1989 (Box 12)
  - JWT plastic paper clip, undated (Box 12)
  - JWT tie pin, undated (Box 12)
  - Necktie, undated (Box 12)
  - Thunderbird bookends, 2002 (Box 12)
  - Toy car, undated (Box 12)
- Audiovisual Materials, 1988-2002 and undated; 8
  - Ad Industry, Self Regulation, undated (Box AV1, Video-cassette RL11676-VHS-001)
  - Advertising Comments by Smithsonian, undated (Box AV1, Video-cassette RL11676-VHS-002)
  - Behind the Scenes, undated (Box AV1, Video-cassette RL11676-VHS-003)
  - Behind the Scenes (Campaign Development), undated (Box AV1, Video-cassette RL11676-VHS-004)
  - Cannes worldwide commercials, undated (Box AV1, Video-cassette RL11676-VHS-005)
  - Finding Solutions, undated (Box AV1, Video-cassette RL11676-VHS-006)
  - Finding Solutions (Campaign Development), undated (Box AV1, Video-cassette RL11676-VHS-007)
  - Research, undated (Box AV1, Video-cassette RL11676-VHS-008)
  - Cannes Awards: Worldwide Commercials, 1999 (Box AV1, Video-cassette RL11676-VHS-009)
  - Client [see notes for contents], undated (Box AV1, Video-cassette RL11676-VHS-010)
  - Dallas Event: Goodyear Rolling Thunder Motorsports Marketing Program, 1999 (Box AV1, Video-cassette RL11676-VHS-011)
  - Goodyear/JWT: "Jump" and "Serious Freedom", undated (Box AV1, Video-cassette RL11676-VHS-012)
  - JWT Heartboeat Logo, undated (Box AV1, Video-cassette RL11676-Bcam-001)
  - JWT Detroit--Advertising: A Commentary by the Smithsonian, undated (Box AV1, Video-cassette RL11676-VHS-014)
  - JWT Detroit--Funny Stuff - Dealer Bull, undated (Box AV1, Video-cassette RL11676-VHS-015)
  - JWT Detroit--Millennium, undated (Box AV1, Video-cassette RL11676-VHS-016)
  - JWT Detroit--Millennium, undated (Box AV1, Video-cassette RL11676-VHS-017)
  - JWT Detroit--Millennium, undated (Box AV1, Video-cassette RL11676-VHS-018)
  - JWT Detroit "Excellent Spots", undated (Box AV1, Video-cassette RL11676-Umatic-001)
    Includes Sprint "Mothers and Sons"; Weather Channel "Evolution"; Miller Anthem; Ken-L Ration "Party Animal"; "Space Hyatt"; Marines "Swords"; Secretaries "Emery"; Chunky "Chunky's Back"; Vic Tanny/Cher; Smarties Candy (London); Ford Topaz (Mexico)
  - JWT New York Media Center Transfer Reel, 2002 (Box AV1, Video-cassette RL11676-VHS-019)
  - Peter Schweitzer "Eyes on Thompson", 1988 (Box AV1, Video-cassette RL11676-Umatic-002)
    Includes Germany "Billboard"; U.S. Mustang "Time To", "Tough Trucks"; Europe Escort "Humps"; Brazil Salvation Army; Argentina "Air Drop", "Pianista", "Only You"; Venezuela "Sierra 280", "Best Thompson Yet"; Mexico "Cougar", "Palenque"; Australia Philishave "Bathroom Sink"; JWT/Ford "Winning"
  - Time Machine "Sell & Spin: A History of Advertising" Part 1, undated (Box AV1, Video-cassette RL11676-Umatic-003)
  - Time Machine "Sell & Spin: A History of Advertising" Part 2, undated (Box AV1, Video-cassette RL11676-Umatic-004)